A Guide to the Papers of Miloš Velimirović, 1955-1992
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of Miloš Velimirović 1955-1992
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
13082
This collection consists of ca. 3,000 items (9 Hollinger boxes, 4 linear feet).
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This collection was given to Special Collections, University of Virginia Library, by Miloš Velimirović, 2610 Dick Woods Road, Charlottesville, Virginia, on March 5, 2004.
Biographical/Historical Information
Retired University of Virginia professor of music, Miloš Velimirović was born December 10, 1922, in Belgrade. He studied at the Belgrade Academy of Music and the University of Belgrade, where he earned a diploma in the history of fine arts. He later earned an MA and PhD at Harvard and then served on the faculty at Yale, 1957-1969, then the University of Wisconsin until 1973 and finally the University of Virginia until his retirement in 1993. A prolific writer of articles in scholarly journals, he also edited numerous other publications and wrote many reviews of books and recordings. Some of his seminal work has focused on the relationship between Slavic and Greek chant melodies of the Slavonic heirmoi.
Scope and Content
The Miloš Velimirović papers consist of ca. 3,000 items (9 Hollinger boxes, 4 linear feet), 1955-1992, donated by musicologist and scholar Miloš Velimirović, a specialist on medieval chants of the Eastern Orthodox Churches and Eastern European music. The bulk of the papers consist of personal and professional correspondence. Personal correspondence includes letters to and from friends and acquaintances and holiday greeting cards and newsletters. Correspondence is mainly in English but other languages include Russian, German, and French. Professional correspondence includes letters to and from publishing companies, itineraries for travel to and reports on academic conferences, letters of recommendations for employment, critiques and editing of scholarly and academic writings, draft manuscripts of journal articles, and copies of papers written by music specialists on a variety of topics.
Arrangement
The papers are arranged alphabetically and reverse chronologically by correspondent.
Contents List
- Gerald Abraham 1972-1973 (Box-folder 1:1)
- Michael Adamis 1969-1974 (Box-folder 1:2)
- Otto Albrecht 1974 (Box-folder 1:3)
- Christine Ammer 1975-1979 (Box-folder 1:4)
- Wulf Arlt 1981 (Box-folder 1:5)
- Elmar Arro 1970-1975 (Box-folder 1:6)
- Robert Atayan 1973-1979 (Box-folder 1:7)
- William Austin 1975-1979 (Box-folder 1:8)
- Hanoch Avenary 1971-1981 (Box-folder 1:9)
- Werner Bachmann 1976-1977 (Box-folder 1:10)
- Eva and Paul Badura-Skoda 1973-1984 (Box-folder 1:11)
- Eva and Paul Badura-Skoda 1971-1972 (Box-folder 1:12)
- Eva and Paul Badura-Skoda 1969-1970 (Box-folder 1:13)
- Jim and Nancy Baker 1971-1977 (Box-folder 1:14)
- Bathja Bayer 1972 (Box-folder 1:15)
- Grant Beglarian 1979-1983 (Box-folder 1:16)
- Gerard H. Behague 1975 (Box-folder 1:17)
- Caroline Bensen 1973-1984 (Box-folder 1:18)
- Karol Berger 1974 (Box-folder 1:19)
- Lawrence Bernstein 1974-1976 (Box-folder 1:20)
- Ilona Borsai 1969-1980 (Box-folder 1:21)
- Cathy Bradley 1992 (Box-folder 1:22)
- Lada Brashovanova-Standcheve 1971-1981 (Box-folder 2:1)
- Joachim Braun 1978-1984 (Box-folder 2:2)
- Maksim Brazhnikov 1962-1975 (Box-folder 2:3)
- Charles Brewer 184 (Box-folder 2:4)
- Clyde Brockett 1982-1983 (Box-folder 2:5)
- Barry and Claire Brook 1967-1984 (Box-folder 2:6)
- Howard Brown 1969-1979 (Box-folder 2:7)
- Neely Bruce 1973-1979 (Box-folder 2:8)
- George Buelow 1973-1992 (Box-folder 2:9)
- Richard von Busch 1972 (Box-folder 2:10)
- Jacques Chailley 1981-1984 (Box-folder 2:11)
- Gheorge Ciobanu 1979-1983 (Box-folder 2:12)
- Dalia Cohen 1969-1981 (Box-folder 2:13)
- Lenore Coral 1971-1977 (Box-folder 2:14)
- Solange Corbin 1969-1970 (Box-folder 2:15)
- Frank Desby 1969-1975 (Box-folder 2:16)
- Gabor Devai 1962-1968 (Box-folder 2:17)
- Bartolomeo Di Salvo 1961-1968 (Box-folder 2:18)
- Sysse Engberg 1965-1974 (Box-folder 2:19)
- Marcy Epstein 1973-1974 (Box-folder 2:20)
- Laurel Fay 1979-1981 (Box-folder 2:21)
- Helmut Federhofer 1969-1973 (Box-folder 2:22)
- Vladimir Fedorov 1963-1975 (Box-folder 2:23)
- Vladimir Fedorov/RISM 1974-1976 (Box-folder 2:24)
- Zdenka Fischmann 1970 (Box-folder 3:1)
- Constantin Floros 1963-1977 (Box-folder 3:2)
- Enrica Follieri 1966-1975 (Box-folder 3:3)
- Robert Fountain/Otto Mueller 1973-1974 (Box-folder 3:4)
- Robert Freeman 1971-1973 (Box-folder 3:5)
- Elliott Galkin 1982-1983 (Box-folder 3:6)
- Edith Gerson-Kiwi 1966-1977 (Box-folder 3:7)
- Evgeni V. Gerzman 1974-1978 (Box-folder 3:8)
- Evgeni V. Gerzman 1979-1985 (Box-folder 3:9)
- Henrik Glahn 1971-1978 (Box-folder 3:10)
- Detlef Gojowy 1983-1985 (Box-folder 3:11)
- Boris Goldovsky 1982-1984 (Box-folder 3:12)
- Jerzy Golos 1967-1973 (Box-folder 3:13)
- Antonina Gove 1975 (Box-folder 3:14)
- Grolier, Inc. 1979 (Box-folder 3:15)
- Grove Dictionary of Music 1970-1974 (Box-folder 3:16)
- Grove Dictionary of Music 1975-1978 (Box-folder 3:17)
- Larry and Marion Gushee, Dale W. Gilbert 1962-1977 (Box-folder 4:1)
- Max Haas 1983 (Box-folder 4:2)
- Louis Hage 1982 (Box-folder 4:3)
- Charles Hamm 1967-1983 (Box-folder 4:4)
- Christian Hannick 1971-1877 (Box-folder 4:5)
- Simon Harris 1964-1965 (Box-folder 4:6)
- Thomas Heck 1973 (Box-folder 4:7)
- Don Henderson 1979-1982 (Box-folder 4:8)
- Harry Hionedes 1965-1971 (Box-folder 4:9)
- Wiley Hitchcock 1968-1975 (Box-folder 4:10)
- Carsten Hoeg 1955-1961 (Box-folder 4:11)
- Carolyn Holmes 1981-1992 (Box-folder 4:12)
- Michel Huglo 1966-1972 (Box-folder 4:13)
- Paul Horecky 1965-1971 (Box-folder 4:14)
- Heinrich Husmann 1972-1983 (Box-folder 4:15)
- Arthur Jacobs 1975-1980 (Box-folder 4:16)
- Roman Jakobson 1980-1983 (Box-folder 4:17)
- Peter Jeffrey 1991-1992 (Box-folder 4:18)
- Peter Jeffrey 1989-1990 (Box-folder 4:19)
- Denise Jourdan-Hemmerdinger 1969-1976 (Box-folder 5:1)
- Masakata (Roger) Kanazawa 1962-1978 (Box-folder 5:2)
- Ruth Katy 1983-1985 (Box-folder 5:3)
- Hugh Kelly 1988 (Box-folder 5:4)
- Ronald Kidd 1973-1977 (Box-folder 5:5)
- Janet Knapp 1970-1975 (Box-folder 5:6)
- Erwin Koschmieder, Johnn von Gardner 1963-1973 (Box-folder 5:7)
- Stan Krebs 1967 (Box-folder 5:8)
- Boris Kremenliev 1974 (Box-folder 5:9)
- Karl Kroger 1970-1980 (Box-folder 5:10)
- Malena Kuss 1983 (Box-folder 5:11)
- Jens Peter and Ruth Larsen 1971-1985 (Box-folder 5:12)
- Kenneth Levy 1971-1992 (Box-folder 5:13)
- Kenneth Levy 1959-1970 (Box-folder 5:14)
- Donald Loach 1974-1977 (Box-folder 5:15)
- Rey Longyear 1974 (Box-folder 5:16)
- Edward Lowinsky 1970 (Box-folder 5:17)
- Martha Maas 1972-1979 (Box-folder 5:18)
- M.W. Mansur 1992 (Box-folder 5:19)
- Fr. Laurence Manusco 1963 (Box-folder 5:20)
- Guy Marco (Garland Publishing) 1979-1983 (Box-folder 5:21)
- Mary Lou[ise] [Lord] 1992 (Box-folder 5:22)
- Giovanni Marzi 1969-1974 (Box-folder 5:23)
- Thomas Mathiesen, Robert Mathiesen, Richard Crocker 1965-1983 (Box-folder 5:24)
- Portia Maultsby 1982 (Box-folder 5:25)
- Marita McClymonds 1984 (Box-folder 5:26)
- Andrew McCredie 1973-1980 (Box-folder 5:27)
- Ernest Mead 1973-1977 (Box-folder 5:28)
- Titus Moisescu 1983-1984 (Box-folder 6:1)
- Vladimir Morosan 1974-1984 (Box-folder 6:2)
- Jaroslav Mracek 1969-1977 (Box-folder 6:3)
- Bruno Nettl 1972-1974 (Box-folder 6:4)
- Frederick Neumann 1977-1985 (Box-folder 6:5)
- Henry Orlov 1968-1979 (Box-folder 6:6)
- Juan Orrego-Salas 1970-1971 (Box-folder 6:7)
- Grigore Pantiru 1970-1974 (Box-folder 6:8)
- Jann Corinne Passler 1978-1982 (Box-folder 6:9)
- Anne Pennington 1970-1981 (Box-folder 6:10)
- Leeman Perkins 1967-1977 (Box-folder 6:11)
- Hrisanta Petrescu 1982-1985 (Box-folder 6:12)
- Milan Postolka 1975 (Box-folder 6:13)
- James Pruett 1971-1977 (Box-folder 6:14)
- Gustave Reese 1960-1974 (Box-folder 6:15)
- Edward Reilly 1975 (Box-folder 6:16)
- Stephen Reinert 1992 (Box-folder 6:17)
- E.J. Revell 1971-1974 (Box-folder 6:18)
- Lukas Richter 1966-1979 (Box-folder 6:19)
- Sister Joan Roccasalvo 1981-1985 (Box-folder 6:20)
- Michael Robinson 1977 (Box-folder 7:1)
- Charlotte Roederer 1969-1970 (Box-folder 7:2)
- Charles Rosen 1972-1974 (Box-folder 7:3)
- Peter Schickele 1975 (Box-folder 7:4)
- Nanna Schiodt 1967-1983 (Box-folder 7:5)
- Leo Schraade 1956-1962 (Box-folder 7:6)
- Boris Schwartz 1970-1980 (Box-folder 7:7)
- Scribner's 1979-1985 (Box-folder 7:8)
- Albert Seay 1976 (Box-folder 7:9)
- John L. Sharpe III 1972 (Box-folder 7:10)
- Kay Shelemay 1984 (Box-folder 7:11)
- Amnon Shiloah 1979 (Box-folder 7:12)
- Paul Shoup 1992 (Box-folder 7:13)
- Boris Shteinpress 1968-1972 (Box-folder 7:14)
- Dmitry Sitkovetsky 1983 (Box-folder 7:15)
- Zbigniew Skowron 1983-1985 (Box-folder 7:16)
- Nicolas Slominsky 1962 (Box-folder 7:17)
- Kent Smith 1974-1983 (Box-folder 7:18)
- George Starks 1984 (Box-folder 7:19)
- Gregory Stathis 1970-1976 (Box-folder 7:20)
- Ruth Steiner 1981-1982 (Box-folder 7:21)
- Robert Stevenson 1975 (Box-folder 7:22)
- Maria Stohr 1965-1966 (Box-folder 7:23)
- Oliver Strunk 1955-1963 (Box-folder 7:24)
- Oliver Strunk 1964-1977 (Box-folder 7:25)
- Jessica Suchy 1979-1982 (Box-folder 7:26)
- Tibor Szasz 1970-1983 (Box-folder 8:1)
- Erik Tawastjerna 1972-1973 (Box-folder 8:2)
- Nicholas Temperley 1975 (Box-folder 8:3)
- Mary Terey-Smith 1962-1965 (Box-folder 8:4)
- Randall Thompson 1976 (Box-folder 8:5)
- Frank Tirro 1969 (Box-folder 8:6)
- Elena Toncheva 1975-1981 (Box-folder 8:7)
- Nikolay Uspenskii 1965-1985 (Box-folder 8:8)
- William (Bill) G. Waite 1962-1964 (Box-folder 8:9)
- John Ward 1964-1974 (Box-folder 8:10)
- Washington Post 1979 (Box-folder 8:11)
- Ed and Lily Waters 1968-1985 (Box-folder 8:12)
- Richard and Mary Wedgewood (Box-folder 8:13)
- Eric Werner 1981 (Box-folder 8:14)
- Phillip Werren 8:15 (Box-folder 8:15)
- Jack Westrup 1962-1969 (Box-folder 8:16)
- Chappell White 1974 (Box-folder 8:17)
- John Reeves White 1975-1976 (Box-folder 8:18)
- Ed Williams 1970-1975 (Box-folder 9:1)
- Ed Williams 1968-1969 (Box-folder 9:2)
- Ed Williams 1967 (Box-folder 9:3)
- Ed Williams 1962-1966 (Box-folder 9:4)
- Eugene K. Wolf 1979 (Box-folder 9:5)
- R. Peter Wolf 1975 (Box-folder 9:6)
- Craig Wright 1984 (Box-folder 9:7)
- Neal Zaslaw 1971-1972 (Box-folder 9:8)
- Elena Zottoviceanu 1979-1980 (Box-folder 9:9)
- M. Velimirović, "Byzantine Musical Traditions among the Slavs," Paper for UVA Symposium 1988 (Box-folder 9:10)